<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article version="5.2" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xila="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude/local-attributes"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <info>
    <title>Introduction to Controlled Languages</title>

   <!--  <author>
      <personname><firstname>Rochelle</firstname><surname>Fisher</surname></personname>
    </author>

    <pubdate>19 June 2025</pubdate> -->
  </info>

  <section>
    <title>What is a Controlled Language?</title>

    <para>A Controlled Language (CL) is set of rules for grammar, sentence
    length, and vocabulary. The rules define a subset of the natural language
    as allowed. Specifically in technical writing, many CLs limit the verbs
    you can use. This enforces consistency for all your documentation and
    conforms to or builds an industry standard for your products.</para>

    <section>
      <title>CL or Taxonomy?</title>

      <para>In general terms, a taxonomy is a structured CL, with parents and
      children. For example, in biology the taxonomy is: kingdom, phylum, class, order, family, genus, species. In
      Artificial Intelligence (AI), the taxonomy may be: AI, Machine Learning,
      Human Crowd-Sourced, Neural Networks, Deep Learning. </para>

      <para>In technical writing, the taxonomy is usually for different
      audiences of a product: system administrator, basic end-user, advanced
      end-user, superuser, C-level decision maker. There will be a default CL,
      with all the rules that apply to all audiences, and a dictionary for
      each personna. For example, a taxonomy for a decision maker will be used
      mainly by Marketing and will allow the word
      <wordasword>leverage</wordasword> with the meaning "to use a foundation
      feature to reach the solution for which the product exists". For all other audiences, the word <wordasword>leverage
      </wordasword>is not allowed, and its alternative is
      <wordasword>use</wordasword>.</para>

      <para>A Taxonomy Manager for a company that creates a shopping app for
      SmartPhones will be in charge of labeling strategies for search results. A Taxonomy Manager for a cyber
      security company will create a CL for different audiences and acquire a
      tool to enforce it. With this ambiguity, we will make our first rule:
      <wordasword>taxonomy</wordasword> is not allowed in this documentation, and
      its alternative is <wordasword>CL</wordasword>(the full vocabulary and rules) or <wordasword>dictionary</wordasword> (a subset of the CL for a specific audience). </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Benefits of a CL</title>

      <para>Adopting and enforcing a CL is the solution to many technical
      writing issues.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>If your organization has a team of writers, the CL enforces
          consistency of the content among the writers. If you have one
          writer, the CL enforces consistency over time among the
          documents.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If you translate your content, the reduced vocabulary and
          grammar and the re-use of matching content, makes translation
          significantly cheaper and often of better quality.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If you have a global market but do not have the budget for
          localization, the CL makes it easier for non-native speakers to read
          and use your documentation correctly. If your documentation is
          online, built-in machine translation (such as Google Translate) will
          give better results.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the technical writers in your organization internalize your
          CL and re-use strategy, their productivity will increase.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Reduce your content by at least 30% without loss
          of information. Concise documentation makes it easier for users to
          find what is relevant to them at the time, makes clear to
          reviewers and stake-holders what is not relevant or incorrect, and
          makes the documented steps easier to follow.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Scope of Project</title>

    <para>This is a personal project of Rochelle Fisher, July 2025. The goal
    is to make a sample of technical writing and a sample of a proprietary CL
    for cybersecurity.</para>

    <para>If you use part, parts, or all of this project for personal use, for
    profit, or for an organization (non-profit or for-profit), you must
    include a reference to this project or its documentation. </para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Reference Example:</emphasis></para>

    <para><literal>Rochelle Fisher, Sample Cyber Security CL, version 1.0, July 2025</literal>.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
	<para>----</para>
	<para>Copyright&#169; 2025 Rochelle Fisher. All Rights Resrved. Original work for private use.</para>
  </section>
</article>
