<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article version="5.2" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xila="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude/local-attributes"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <info>
    <title>What Now?</title>

    <!-- <author>
      <personname><firstname>Rochelle</firstname><surname>Fisher</surname></personname>
    </author> -->

    <!-- <pubdate>7 July 2025</pubdate> -->
  </info>
  <para>You have a dictionary in progress. You must go through all the words, update the definitions
    and rules as you go. </para>
  <para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <para>When you are done with the top twenty or thirty words, sort your dictionary to see at
        the words with only one count. These words will be easy to set as not allowed, commands, or
        misspellings. </para>
      <listitem>
        <para>If the word is not allowed, set its values. Make sure the alternative words are
          allowed.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If the word is a command, in <guilabel>PoS</guilabel>, enter
            <literal>command</literal>. Set it to <guilabel>Allowed</guilabel> =
            <literal>T</literal>. Make sure your style guide says to wrap commands in relevant
          elements.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If the word is a mistake, in <guilabel>PoS</guilabel>, enter
            <literal>misspelling</literal>. When your content is fixed for this mistake, you can
          remove it from the dictionary.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If the word is correct and allowed, investigate. If it is a word for a specific
          audience, set it to <guilabel>Allowed</guilabel> for that audience. If a product owner or sponsor wants it for
          everyone, discuss why.</para>
        <para>For example, <wordasword>absent</wordasword> is used one time, in the phrase
            <wordasword>absent a route</wordasword>. This is a specific network configuration
          action. It is correct. We allow it for the user, sysadmin, and internal audiences. But we
          do not want it in the UX microcopy or C-level marketing.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <para>You will need a checker tool. You can acquire the tool before you complete the dictionary.
    You can ask a Python developer to make a script that returns an email or a webpage with results
    (unallowed words used, rules as reminders on allowed words, and unknown words). Or you can
    acquire an AI tool that integrates with your source CCMS. The important thing is that your
    dictionary is used. It is a dynamic tool for all content creators in your organization. </para>
  <para/>
 </article> 
