<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article version="5.2" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xila="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude/local-attributes"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <info>
    <title>Work the Words - First Steps</title>

    <!-- <author>
      <personname><firstname>Rochelle</firstname><surname>Fisher</surname></personname>
    </author> -->

    <!-- <pubdate>19 June 2025</pubdate> -->
  </info>

  <section>
   <para>With three small samples of cybersecurity documentation from different organizations, the python script gave us 4755 unique words.
   Your sample should be much larger. Our goal is to make a cybersecurity dictionary of about 1000 words. This does not include product names
   or company-specific words. </para>
   <para>Scheduling: The average effort is 20 words each hour. We can expect this dictionary to require 238 hours (about 30 working days) to complete.</para>
   <procedure><title>To work through the words to create your dictionary:</title>
		<step>Import the dictionary CSV file to a spreadsheet.<para>We will use Google Sheets. You can use Microsoft Excel or 
		similar.</para><para>Our Python script uses a pipe ( | ) as a delimiter between the word and its frequency of use. When you import 
		the CSV, set the pipe as the delimiter, to get the word list in column A and the frequency in column B.</para></step>
		<step>Change row 1 to be these headers: Word, Count, Part of Speech, Definition, Good Example, Bad Example, Allowed?, Audience, Alt1, Alt2</step>
		<step>If there are rows between the header row and the first word, delete them.</step>
		<step>The script sorted the list by highest frequency to lowest. Start with the words most used. These will be the easiest.
			</step>
		<step>Set the Part of Speech.
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>A typical result for the most used words are the name of your organization or product.
				Set the part of speech as Name. This lets you filter for these nouns which may change more often 
				than regular nouns. And, you will have variables for these names, which should be ignored by the checker tool.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Enter the part of speech for the other most common words. When you get to a word that could be used in 
				multiple ways, enter TBD and stop.</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		
	</step>
		<step>If the word is a name or common word, such as <emphasis>the that this from</emphasis>, you can leave the Definition blank.
		For all other words:
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>If you do not allow the word, do not enter a definition. Enter an alternative word. If there are multiple
			alteratives, enter one word in each ALT column. You can add more ALT columns if required. In the Allowed column, enter F
			(for false).</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>If you allow the word, enter a definition. Leave the ALT columns blank.</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		</step>
		<step>If you can easily copy an exmaple of the word, do it now. If the word is not allowed, paste the example from your sample in Bad Example.
		In Good Example, enter the rewritten phrase or sentence with the correct allowed alternative.
		If the word is allowed, paste your sample in Good Example, and leave Bad Example blank. In the Allowed column, enter T (for true).
		</step>
		<step>In the Allowed column, enter T (for true) or F (for false).</step>
		<step>In the Audience column, enter <emphasis>all</emphasis>, or create a list of your audience personas on a separate tab and then create a 
		data validation for this column, to select the persona from the list.</step>
   </procedure>
  </section>
  <section>
	<title>Examples</title>
	
  </section>
</article>