<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article version="5.2" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xila="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude/local-attributes"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <info>
    <title>Project Tasks</title>

   <!--  <author>
      <personname><firstname>Rochelle</firstname><surname>Fisher</surname></personname>
    </author> 

    <pubdate>21 August 2025</pubdate>-->
  </info>
  <formalpara>
    <title>Task: Communicate</title>
    <para>Expected Output: Buy-in from the technical writers to be motivated to create the CL, to use it daily, to learn the rules, and to maintain changes as required.</para>  
  </formalpara>
  <para>Owner: Manager of Technical Writers or higher</para>
  <para>Est. Effort: 1 - 5 hrs</para>
  
  <formalpara>
    <title>Task: Collect Documentation</title>
    <para>Expected Output: One aggregate text file of all documentation of a product</para>  
  </formalpara>
  <para>Owner: Technical Writer</para>
  <para>Est. Effort: 5 - 9 hrs</para>
  
  <formalpara>
    <title>Task: Create Dictionary File</title>
    <para>Expected Output: Spreadsheet with all unique words, the count of each word in your documentation, and columns for linguistic analysis</para>  
  </formalpara>
  <para>Owner: Developer (possible tech writer with Python experience)</para>
  <para>Est. Effort: 1 - 4 hrs</para>
    
  <formalpara>
    <title>Task: Acquire or develop checker tool</title>
    <para>Expected Output: A tool that will tell writers when they do not conform with the Dictionary, replacement words or content to rewrite, and 
      rules that explain why. Most often, if you develop a tool in-house, it will not integrate with the authoring tool. Writers will 
      get results only after they wrote a topic or book. If you acquire a tool, make sure it integrates with your authoring tool,
      for on-the-fly checks and fast rewrites.</para>  
  </formalpara>
  <para>Owner: Technical Writer / Decision-Maker</para>
  <para>Your technical writer researches the features and cost of tools, such as Writer and Jasper. If the cost is out of 
    your budget for documentation, you will require the time and services of a developer. The technical writer should manage
    the developer's requirements and expected output.</para>
  <para>Est. Effort: Depends on solution</para>
  <para>The tech writer can begin working the Dictionary before the tool is acquired or created. If you acquire a tool before the writer begins,
    it may save some days that might be required to change the Dictionary structure to import properly to the tool.</para>
       
  <formalpara>
    <title>Task: Create Vocabulary Values in Dictionary File</title>
    <para>Expected Output: A complete vocabulary in a spreadsheet or acquired tool, with words and phrases, set to allowed or not allowed, each with a specific defintion and part of speech,
      with examples and rules to help writers remain consistent.</para>  
  </formalpara>
  <para>Owner: Technical Writer</para>
 
  <para>Est. Effort: 20 words/hour</para>
  <para>
    For a Dictionary with 10K - 50K words, and tech writers who work on it as a side project, plan for one work-year.
  </para>
 
  
     
 </article> 
