<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article version="5.2" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xila="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude/local-attributes"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <info>
    <title>Work the Words</title>

    <!-- <author>
      <personname><firstname>Rochelle</firstname><surname>Fisher</surname></personname>
    </author> -->

    <!-- <pubdate>19 June 2025</pubdate> -->
  </info>

  <section>
	  <title>First Words</title>
   <para>With three small samples of cybersecurity documentation from different organizations, the Python script gave us 4755 unique words.
   Your sample should be much larger. Our goal is to create a cybersecurity dictionary of approximately 1,000 words. This does not include product names
   or company-specific words. </para>
   <para>Effort: The average effort is 20 words each hour. We can expect this dictionary to require 238 hours (about 30 working days) to complete.</para>
   <procedure><title>To work through the words to create your dictionary:</title>
		<step>Import the dictionary CSV file to a spreadsheet.<para>We will use Google Sheets. You can use Microsoft Excel or 
		similar.</para><para>Our Python script uses a pipe ( | ) as a delimiter between the word and its frequency of use. When you import the CSV, set the pipe as the delimiter, to get the word list in column A and the frequency in column B.
		</para></step>
		<step>Change row 1 to be these headers: Word, Count, Part of Speech, Definition, Good Example, Bad Example, Allowed?, Audience, Alt1, Alt2</step>
		<step>If there are rows between the header row and the first word, delete them.</step>
		<step>The script sorted the list by highest frequency to lowest. Start with the words most used. These will be the easiest.
			</step>
		<step>Set the Part of Speech (PoS).
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>A typical result for the most used words are the name of your organization or product.
				Set the PoS as Name. This lets you filter for these nouns which may change more often 
				than regular nouns. And, you will have variables for these names, which should be ignored by the checker tool.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Enter the PoS for the other most common words. When you get to a word that could be used in 
				multiple ways, enter TBD and stop.</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		
	</step>
		<step>If the word is a name or common word, such as <emphasis>the that this from</emphasis>, you can leave the Definition blank.
		For all other words:
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>If you do not allow the word, do not enter a definition. Enter an alternative word. If there are multiple
			alteratives, enter one word in each ALT column. You can add more ALT columns if required. In the Allowed column, enter F
			(for false).</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>If you allow the word, enter a definition. Leave the ALT columns blank.</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		</step>
		<step>If you can easily copy an exmaple of the word, do it now. If the word is not allowed, paste the example from your sample in Bad Example.
		In Good Example, enter the rewritten phrase or sentence with the correct allowed alternative.
		If the word is allowed, paste your sample in Good Example, and leave Bad Example blank. In the Allowed column, enter T (for true).
		</step>
		<step>In the Allowed column, enter T (for true) or F (for false).</step>
		<step>In the Audience column, enter <emphasis>all</emphasis>, or create a list of your audience personas on a separate tab and then create a 
		data validation for this column, to select the persona from the list.</step>
   </procedure>
  </section>
  <section>
	<title>Examples of the First Words</title>
	  <itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
		<para>In our example, one of the product or company names is the word with the highest frequency. We set its PoS as <emphasis>name</emphasis> and set it to be <wordasword>Allowed</wordasword>.
		We set the audience to <emphasis>all</emphasis>. We do not set a value for the other columns yet.</para>
	<imagedata fileref="images/words01/png" />
	</listitem>
		<listitem><para>
			In the next top 20 words, we have many that are clearly to be allowed: <emphasis>this that will with from your</emphasis>. These are pronouns, prepositions, and modular verbs. In this case, it does not give a lot of information 
			to define the PoS. Is <emphasis>that</emphasis> a pronoun, adverb, conjunction, or determiner? In a technical writing dictionary for native speakers, it does not matter. We set up a rule that we do not use minimalist rules. 
			If <emphasis>that</emphasis> helps make a sentence easier to understand, we use it. You can set a definition forf <emphasis>will</emphasis>, to make it clear that the use of will as a part of a future-tense verbal phrase is allowed, 
			but it is not allowed as a verb to mean "to desire" or as a noun to mean "legal declaration of disposal of property after death".
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Next we have words that are industry standard for software technical writing: <emphasis>
			introduction
user
data
attributes
attribute
example
organisation</emphasis>. At some point, we may require a specific deinition for some of these words. For now, we set the PoS, set to Allowed, and set audience to all.</para>
			<note>Note that <emphasis>attribute</emphasis> and <emphasis>attributes</emphasis> are two items. We restrict the values of the Word and ALT columns to one word or phrase to prepare for a checker tool that might be simple Python script.
			If you know that you will use an AI-driven tool, such as writer.com or jasper.ai, change the dictionary to work with the aquired tool.
			</note>
			<para>See <emphasis>organisation</emphasis>. We know we need this word, but this spelling is British. We know our rules will tell us to use American spelling. In this case, we will make a decision for our dictionary without
			analysis, or to put it more accurately, despite analysis. The spelling of <emphasis>organisation</emphasis> is the most commonly used form, but we will not use it. We will use the American spelling.
				<procedure>
					<step><para>Sort the complete range of dictionary alphabetically, by <wordasword>Word</wordasword>.</para></step>
					<step><para>Set <emphasis>organization</emphasis> and <emphasis>organizations</emphasis> as allowed (T in <wordasword>Allowed</wordasword>).</para></step>
					<step><para>Set the British <emphasis>organisation</emphasis> and <emphasis>organisations</emphasis> as not allowed (F in <wordasword>Allowed</wordasword>).</para></step>
					<step><para>In the allowed words, set the definition: <literal>nonspecific body of people with a purpose</literal></para></step>
					<step><para>In ALT1 for <emphasis>organisation</emphasis> and <emphasis>organisations</emphasis>, enter <emphasis>organization</emphasis> and <emphasis>organizations</emphasis>.</para></step>
				</procedure>	
				
			</para>
			<note>Why not add <emphasis>organizational</emphasis> on the fly? Answer: It is used only one time. We will analyze the text and hope to find a more common rewrite in that one sentence.</note>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	  <para>Sort the range by Count. We are done with the easiest words. Next: analyze words in their syntax and by content to make decisions for the dictionary.</para>

  </section>
</article>
