<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article version="5.2" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xila="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude/local-attributes"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <info>
    <title>Getting Started with the Dictionary</title>

    <!-- <author>
      <personname><firstname>Rochelle</firstname><surname>Fisher</surname></personname>
    </author> -->

    <!-- <pubdate>19 June 2025</pubdate> -->
  </info>

 <section><title>Work the First Words</title>
   <para>The first words that you set up in your dictionary will be the easiest and will have the most impact. </para>
   <para>Prerequisites: Have the dictionary file in a spreadsheet. Make sure it is sorted for COUNT.</para>
   <para>Effort: This will require less than an hour.</para>
   <procedure><title>To work through the most used words in your dictionary:</title>
		
   	<step><para>In the word with the highest count, set the Part of Speech (PoS).</para>
			<para>A typical result for the most used words are the names of your organization or product.
				ASD-STE calls these <emphasis>technical names</emphasis>. Set the <guilabel>PoS</guilabel> 
				of the technical names in the top results as <literal>Name</literal>.</para>
   		<para>
   			This lets you filter for proper nouns which change more often than regular nouns. </para>
   		<para>
				For example, the company name will change if your organization delivers a white label product.</para>
		</step>
		<step>
			<para>Enter the PoS for the other most common words, such as <wordasword>the that this from</wordasword>. When you get to a word that is may be used in multiple parts of speech and 
			is not a common word for all English content, skip it.</para>
		</step>
		
   	<step><para>In the <guilabel>Allowed</guilabel> column, enter <literal>T</literal> (for true) or <literal>F</literal> (for false).</para>
   		<para>Most of these first words will be allowed.</para></step>
   	<step><para>In the <guilabel>Audience</guilabel> column, enter <literal>all</literal>
   		or select a persona from the list, if you are sure this word will be allowed only for this persona.</para></step>
   </procedure>
  </section>
  <section>
	<title>Examples of the First Words</title>
  	<para>In our example,
  		one of the product
  		or company names
  		is the word with the
  		highest frequency. This should be your most used word too.</para>
  	<table>
  		<title>The Most Used Word</title>
  		<tgroup cols="5">
  			<thead>
  				<row>
  					<entry>Word</entry>
  					
  					<entry>PoS</entry>
  					<entry>Definition</entry>
  					<entry>Allowed?</entry>
  					<entry>Audience</entry>
  					<!--<entry>ALT</entry>-->
  				</row>
  			</thead>
  			<tbody>
  				<row>
  					<entry><emphasis>company or product name</emphasis></entry>
  					<entry><literal>Name</literal></entry>
  					<entry><emphasis>Add your marketing definition.</emphasis></entry>
  					
  					<entry><literal>T</literal></entry>
  					<entry><literal>all</literal></entry>
  				</row>
  			</tbody>
  		</tgroup>
  	</table>
	<para>
			In the top words, we have many that are clearly to be allowed: <wordasword>this that will with from your</wordasword>. These are pronouns, prepositions, and modular verbs. 
			In a technical writing dictionary for native speakers, it does not give a lot of information to define the PoS. Is <wordasword>that</wordasword> a pronoun, adverb, conjunction, or determiner? 
		Enter any reasonable value for the PoS. </para><para>
			In our style guide, we set a rule that we do not use minimalist rules. 
			If <wordasword>that</wordasword> helps make a sentence easier to understand, we use it. 
			</para>
  	<table>
  		<title>Most Used Words</title>
  		<tgroup cols="6">
  			<thead>
  				<row>
  					<entry>Word</entry>
  					<entry>Count</entry>
  					<entry>PoS</entry>
  					<entry>Definition</entry>
  					<entry>Allowed?</entry>
  					<entry>Audience</entry>
  				</row>
  			</thead>
  			<tbody>
  				<row>
  					<entry><literal>this</literal></entry>
  					<entry><literal>730</literal></entry>
  					<entry><literal>pronoun</literal></entry>
  					<entry><emphasis>blank</emphasis></entry>
  					<entry><literal>T</literal></entry>
  					<entry><literal>all</literal></entry>
  				</row>
  				<row>
  					<entry><literal>that</literal></entry>
  					<entry><literal>706</literal></entry>
  					<entry><literal>pronoun</literal></entry>
  					<entry><emphasis>blank</emphasis></entry>
  					<entry><literal>T</literal></entry>
  					<entry><literal>all</literal></entry>
  				</row>
  				<row>
  					<entry><literal>will</literal></entry>
  					<entry><literal>667</literal></entry>
  					<entry><literal>verb</literal></entry>
  					<entry><emphasis>sets future tense of main verb (we defined this word to differentiate from its other definitions)</emphasis></entry>
  					<entry><literal>T</literal></entry>
  					<entry><literal>all</literal></entry>
  				</row>
  				<row>
  					<entry><literal>with</literal></entry>
  					<entry><literal>612</literal></entry>
  					<entry><literal>preposition</literal></entry>
  					<entry><emphasis>blank</emphasis></entry>
  					<entry><literal>T</literal></entry>
  					<entry><literal>all</literal></entry>
  				</row>
  				<row>
  					<entry><literal>from</literal></entry>
  					<entry><literal>501</literal></entry>
  					<entry><literal>preposition</literal></entry>
  					<entry><emphasis>blank</emphasis></entry>
  					<entry><literal>T</literal></entry>
  					<entry><literal>all</literal></entry>
  				</row>
  				<row>
  					<entry><literal>your</literal></entry>
  					<entry><literal>376</literal></entry>
  					<entry><literal>pronoun</literal></entry>
  					<entry><emphasis>blank</emphasis></entry>
  					<entry><literal>T</literal></entry>
  					<entry><literal>all</literal></entry>
  				</row>
  			
  			</tbody>
  		</tgroup>
  	</table>
		
	
<para>We have words that are industry standard for software technical writing: <wordasword>
			introduction
user
data
attributes
attribute
example
organisation</wordasword>. </para>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>We set the <guilabel>PoS</guilabel> and <guilabel>Definition</guilabel> for our words. We
			set <guilabel>Allowed</guilabel> to <literal>T</literal> and <guilabel>Audience</guilabel> to <literal>all</literal>.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Notice that <wordasword>attribute</wordasword> and <wordasword>attributes</wordasword> are two items. </para>
			<para>
				We restrict the values of the <guilabel>Word</guilabel> and <guilabel>ALT</guilabel>
				columns to one word or phrase, to prepare for a checker tool that might be a simple Python script. This is 
			different from the way ASD-STE is written, but if you begin with this restriction, it will be easier later.</para>
			<para>If you know that you will use a specific AI-driven tool, such as writer.com or jasper.ai, change the dictionary 
				headers and values to work with the acquired tool.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>See <wordasword>organisation</wordasword>. We know we need this word, but this spelling is British. We know our rules will tell us to use American spelling. In this case, we will make a decision for our dictionary without
				analysis, or to put it more accurately, despite analysis. The spelling of <wordasword>organisation</wordasword> is the most commonly used form, but we will not use it. We will use the American spelling.</para>
			<procedure>
				<step><para>Sort the complete range of dictionary alphabetically, by <wordasword>Word</wordasword>.</para></step>
				<step><para>Set <wordasword>organization</wordasword> and <wordasword>organizations</wordasword> as allowed (<literal>T</literal> in <guilabel>Allowed</guilabel>).</para></step>
				<step><para>Set the British <wordasword>organisation</wordasword> and <wordasword>organisations</wordasword> as not allowed (<literal>F</literal> in <guilabel>Allowed</guilabel>).</para></step>
				<step><para>In the allowed words, set the definition: <literal>nonspecific body of people with a purpose</literal>.</para><para>We will use <wordasword>organization</wordasword> for a 
						company, nonprofit org, military base, and all similar bodies.</para></step>
				<step><para>In ALT1 for <wordasword>organisation</wordasword> and <wordasword>organisations</wordasword>, enter <wordasword>organization</wordasword> and <wordasword>organizations</wordasword>.</para></step>
			</procedure>
			<para>When we sorted by Word to see all the issues of <wordasword>organi*</wordasword>, we saw <wordasword>organizational</wordasword>, with a COUNT of <literal>1</literal>. 
				Why not add <wordasword>organizational</wordasword> on the fly? 
				Answer: It is used only one time. We will analyze the text and find a more common rewrite in that one sentence. 
				Or maybe that one instance is for <wordasword>Organizational Unit (OU)</wordasword> in Active Directory. 
				If so, we will make that phrase a "word".</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
			
<para>NEXT:  When you are done with the most used words that you want to complete now (best practice: stop after an hour), sort the range by Count.
	We will analyze the words that are most likely to be NOT allowed: words used only one time. After that, go through the words in 
the order that best works for you.</para>

  </section>
</article>
